Register of the Joseph Warren Stilwell papers 51001
Hoover Institution Archives
- Incremental Materials, 1910-2002
  - Clippings and printed matter, 1921-1992 (Box-folder 101: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1919-1989
    - Easterbrook, Nancy S., 1975-1989 (Box-folder 101: 2)
      Includes correspondence between Nancy S. Easterbrook and Robert D. Lichty, Li-Jen sun, and T. P. Taggert.
    - Stilwell, Joseph W.
      - General
        - Undated (Box-folder 101: 3)
        - 1921-1946 (Box-folder 101: 4)
      - Stilwell, Winifred A.
        - Undated (Box-folder 101: 5)
        - 1919-1945 (Box-folder 101: 6)
    - Stilwell, Winifred A.
      - General
        - Undated (Box-folder 101: 7)
        - 1942-1948 (Box-folder 101: 8)
        - 1942-1957, including with H. H. Fisher, Hoover Institution, April 1951 (Box-folder 101: 9)
      - Letters of condolences
        See also PERSONAL AND FAMILY FILE, B-19.
        - Undated (Box-folder 101: 10)
        - 1946-1948 (Box-folder 101: 11)
  - Military file
    - General, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 101: 12)
    - Circulars, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 101: 13)
    - Clippings and printed matter
      - Undated (Box-folder 101: 14)
      - 1918-1982 (Box-folder 101: 15)
    - Correspondence
      - Undated (Box-folder 101: 16)
      - 1942-1987, including with Joseph W. Stilwell (Box-folder 101: 17)
    - ID cards of Joseph W. Stilwell, one card with right thumb print, issued May 20, 1944, by Frank Milani, authorizing him to carry on investigations in the CBI Theater; and one with right index finger print, issued May 9, 1946, by Atomic Bomb Test Joint Task Force One, identifying him as staff associated with Project Crossroads (Box-folder 102: 1)
    - Lists, including of war materials, May 2, 1942, and of proposed shipments for China, 1942 May-October (Box-folder 102: 2)
    - Maps and sketches, undated (Box-folder 102: 3)
      Includes maps of Luzon and Northern Philippines navigation chart.
    - Memoranda
      - Undated, on White Paper on U.S. relations with China (Box-folder 102: 4)
      - 1942-1944, including for Joseph W. Stilwell (Box-folder 102: 5)
    - Notebook of Spanish notes, 1914 (Box-folder 102: 6)
    - Notes
      - Conference notes, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 102: 7)
      - Lecture notes and miscellany, 1914-1918 (Box-folder 102: 8-13)
    - Reports (Box 91)
      - Undated
        - "Biennial Report: The Chief of Staff of the United States Army to the Secretary of War, July 1, 1943 – June 30, 1945" (Box-folder 103: 1)
        - "Report by the Supreme Commander to the Combined Chiefs of Staff on the Operations in Europe of the Allied Expeditionary Force, June 6, 1944 – May 8, 1945" (Box-folder 103: 2)
      - 1938-1942 (Box-folder 103: 3)
        Includes reports on Joseph W. Stilwell's observations regarding Chinese fighting during a battle at Teian, October 23-28, 1938.
      - Reports by Dwight D. Eisenhower and George C. Marshall, 1945 (Box-folder 103: 4)
    - Miscellany, 1911-1993 (Box-folder 103: 5)
  - Speeches and writings
    - General
      - Collected writings, "Our Stilwell Heritage: Writings of Ole Pappy, and others," arranged by Deborah J. Bunce, 1999 (Box-folder 103: 5)
        See box 88, folders 9-12.
      - List of Joseph W. Stilwell's writings as sent to George T. Bye, January 31, 1949, and a letter to the editor, Wall Street Journal, by I. Ridgeway Trimble, August 30, 1974, which quotes some of Joseph W. Stilwell's comments. (Box-folder 103: 6)
    - "All Is Not Gold that Glitters," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 7)
    - "The Big Automobile Race," short story, undated (Box-folder 103: 8)
    - "Bits from China," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 9)
    - "Boy Scout Rally," speech, undated (Box-folder 103: 10)
    - "The British," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 11)
    - "China for Player and Spectator," thoughts for speech, undated (Box-folder 103: 12)
    - "The Chinese Overseer," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 13)
    - "Chinese Revolt against the Mongols," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 14)
    - "Chinese Village," essay, undated (Box-folder 103: 15)
    - "Defense of the Regular Army," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 16)
    - "Diagnosis Minimus: A Lay of Ancient Rome," short story, undated (Box-folder 103: 17)
    - "The Dowager Empress: Tzu His," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 18)
    - "Gillem's Loss," comments on different personalities, undated (Box-folder 103: 19)
    - "Haphazard Conversations," short story, undated (Box-folder 103: 20)
    - "How Can the Battalion Commander Play His Role Best?" article, undated (Box-folder 103: 21)
    - "Infiltration," lecture, Fort Benning, Georgia, undated (Box-folder 103: 22)
    - "It Is Better to Be Lucky than Rich," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 23)
    - "Modern Warfare: Infantry Versus Tank and Dive-Bomber," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 24)
    - "The Modernization of China," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 25)
    - "Moving Picture Show," short story, undated (Box-folder 103: 26)
    - "News Flashes," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 27)
    - "Odds and Ends," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 28)
    - "On the Tehuantepec Trail," short story, undated (Box-folder 103: 29)
    - Poems, undated (Box-folder 103: 30)
      Includes list.
    - "Politeness - or 'Face'," article, undated (Box-folder 103: 31)
    - "A Protest on Leadership," essay, undated (Box-folder 104: 1)
    - "Rambling along Chinese Trail," short story, undated (Box-folder 104: 2)
    - "Reminiscing for the Children," article, undated (Box-folder 104: 3)
    - "Stories by Ole Pappy," collection of stories, undated (Box-folder 104: 4)
    - "The T'ai P'ing Invasion of the North, 1853–1855," article, undated (Box-folder 104: 5)
    - "Thoughts on the U.S. Army," essay, undated (Box-folder 104: 6)
    - "War and Work on the Ledo Road (Burma)," talk, undated (Box-folder 104: 7)
    - "Hong-Kong to Manila," descriptive letter, McKinley, Manila, Philippines, 1911 December 17 (Box-folder 104: 8)
    - "The Amateur Doctor," short story, 1921 (Box-folder 104: 9)
    - "A Chinese Inn," short story, 1921 (Box-folder 104: 10)
    - "How to Travel on a Chinese Railroad," short story, 1921 (Box-folder 104: 11)
    - "Official Reception for Distinguished Visitors," short story, 1921 (Box-folder 104: 12)
    - "The Old Taoist Priest from Yunnan," article, 1921 (Box-folder 104: 13)
    - "Paul Revere's Ride," short story, 1921 (Box-folder 104: 14)
    - "The Shih Li Pu Beggars," short story, 1921 (Box-folder 104: 15)
    - "Yellow River Road," short story, 1921 (Box-folder 104: 16)
    - "Excerpts from My Chinese Diary," short story, 1922 (Box-folder 104: 17)
    - "On s'amuse," short story, 1922 (Box-folder 104: 18)
    - "An Unorthodox Chinese Diary," expanded diary, 1922 (Box-folder 104: 19)
    - Remarks on "The Normal Life of a Normal Chinese Woman," Fort Woman's Club, 1923-1925 (Box-folder 104: 20)
    - Armistice Day Celebration, musical program, Fort Benning, Georgia, 1924 November 11 (Box-folder 104: 21)
    - "Hsu Chow Fu," article, 1927 (Box-folder 104: 22)
    - "What Is the Issue in China?" article, 1927 (Box-folder 104: 23)
    - "Bleat from the Orient," article, 1928 (Box-folder 104: 24)
    - "Psychology of Orientals," article, 1929 (Box-folder 104: 25)
    - Lectures, Fort Benning, Georgia, 1930-1932 (Box-folder 104: 26)
    - "Case of Jim Averill," short story, 1933 (Box-folder 104: 27)
    - "Hinky Dink and the Chinese Platter," article, 1933 (Box-folder 104: 28)
    - "Odyssey of a Shave-Tail," San Diego, California, short story, 1933 (Box-folder 104: 29)
    - "The Siege of Badres," short story, 1933 (Box-folder 104: 30)
    - "Cock-Tail Parties in Peking," article, 1935 (Box-folder 104: 31)
    - "Future Developments in China," article, 1935 (Box-folder 104: 32)
    - "Guerrilla Warfare," article, circa 1936 (Box-folder 104: 33)
    - "Communism in China," article, 1937 (Box-folder 104: 34)
    - "The Dragon Goes to Kashgar: Tso Tsung T'ang and the Mohammedan Rebellion," article, 1937 (Box-folder 104: 35)
    - "Just a Few Remarks by Ole Pappy," article, 1937 July (Box-folder 104: 36)
    - "Chinese Notes," article, 1937 August 12 (Box-folder 104: 37)
    - "Let's Go," song for the 7th Division Song Book, Fort Ord, California, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 104: 38)
    - Talk to officers and men of the 7th division, Fort Ord, California, 1941 July 26 (Box-folder 104: 39)
      Holograph draft.
    - Remarks, Conference on Policy in China, Cairo, Egypt, 1943 December 6 (Box-folder 104: 40)
      Holograph. Includes related materials.
    - Speech, Greek rally, San Francisco, California, 1944 November (Box-folder 104: 41)
    - Excerpts from remarks, Monterey, California, 1944 November 16 (Box-folder 104: 42)
    - "Let's Finish the Fight: War Bond Drive," remarks, 1944 November 26 (Box-folder 104: 43)
    - "On Taking Command of the Army Ground Forces," remarks, 1945 (Box-folder 104: 44)
    - Address, Pre-Campaign Luncheon for the Red Cross 1945 War Fund, New York, 1945 February 19 (Box-folder 104: 45)
    - "Army Day," remarks, 1945 April 7 (Box-folder 105: 1)
    - Recorded message from the China-Burma-India Theater at the end of the war with Germany, 1945 May (Box-folder 105: 2)
    - Speech, Detroit, Michigan, 1945 May 16 (Box-folder 105: 3)
    - Statement, Salute to the GI's of the United Nations, New York, 1945 May 31 (Box-folder 105: 4)
      Holograph and typescript. Includes a letter from Paul L. Jones to Edwin S. Smith, May 21, 1945.
    - Graduation speech, West Point, New York, 1945 June (Box-folder 105: 5)
      Holograph fragment and typescript.
    - "Message for G.I. Joe," remarks, circa 1945 September (Box-folder 105: 6)
      Typescript. Includes a letter from Joseph W. Stilwell to William T. Nichols, September 5, 1945. See also PERSONAL AND FAMILY FILE/B-15.
  - Subject file, 1938-2002
    - Balkans, undated (Box-folder 105: 7)
    - China
      - General (Box-folder 105: 8)
      - War Messages and Other Selections, May-ling Soong Chiang (Madame Chiang Kai-shek), 1938, presented to Joseph W. Stilwell, 1938 September 22 (Box-folder 105: 9)
      - Highway Transportation History, edited by the Commission of the Communication and Transportation Department, Xansi province, China, 1988 (Box-folder 105: 10)
    - Dedication of General Joseph W. Stilwell Museum, Chongqing, China, 1991 October 11-13
      - General (Chinese language materials) (Box-folder 106: 1)
      - "I Was There, too, When General Stilwell Was in Chongqing," article by Ignace Liu (Box-folder 106: 2)
      - "On General Stilwell," talk by Mr. Epstein (Box-folder 106: 3)
      - "The Strategic Significance of Sino-Indian Highway," speech, Luo Hong Zhang, Stilwell Seminar (Box-folder 106: 4)
      - Speech by Huang Hua, Opening Ceremony, Stilwell Seminar (Box-folder 106: 5)
      - "Understanding American Culture," speech by Betsy Geist (Box-folder 106: 6)
      - Speech by Nancy S. Easterbrook. (Box-folder 106: 7)
        Includes notes.
    - Stilwell stamp.
      See also INCREMENTAL MATERIALS/Photographs/box 109/folder 3.
      - General, 2000 August 24 (Box-folder 106: 8)
        Includes first day issue.
      - Clippings and printed matter, 2000 (Box-folder 106: 9)
      - Correspondence
        - Bush, George H. W., 1993 (Box-folder 106: 10)
        - CBS Inc., 1991 (Box-folder 106: 11)
        - China-Burma-India Veterans Association, Inc., 1991-1992 (Box-folder 106: 12)
        - Citizen's Stamp Advisory Committee, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 106: 13)
        - Easterbrook, John, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 106: 14)
        - Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, 1990 (Box-folder 106: 15)
        - Nixon, Richard, 1991 (Box-folder 106: 16)
        - Runyon, Marvin, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 106: 17)
          Includes correspondence with George Bush, Barry Goldwater, Robert S. McNamara, Caspar W. Weinberger, and others.
        - U.S. Congress. House of Representatives, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 106: 18)
          Includes correspondence of Newt Gingrich, Norman Mineta, and others.
        - U.S. Congress. Senate, 1990-1996 (Box-folder 106: 19)
          Includes correspondence of Daniel Inouye, John Warner, Joseph Lieberman, Pete Wilson, Sam Nunn, Tom Campbell, and others.
        - University of Arizona, 1994 (Box-folder 106: 20)
        - University of Georgia, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 106: 21)
          Includes correspondence of Dean Rusk.
        - West, Michael, 1990 (Box-folder 106: 22)
      - News releases, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 106: 23)
      - Speeches
        - John Easterbrook, grandson of General Stilwell, First Day of Issue Ceremony, Providence, Rhode Island, August 24, 2000, and China-Burma-India Veterans Association Reunion, Houston, Texas, 2000 August 25 (Box-folder 106: 24)
        - Susan Mai Easterbrook Cole, great granddaughter of General Stilwell, Stilwell Hall, Fort Ord, California, 2000 August 25 (Box-folder 106: 25)
  - Miscellany, 1910-1995 (Box-folder 106: 26-27)
    Includes also Peking for the Army and Navy, Marcus R. Ogden, 1935, and Peking Utility Book, 1937-1938 and 1938-1939.
  - Oversize materials, undated (Box 107)
    Eight photocopies of maps of Burma.
  - Scrapbooks, 1889-1928 (Box 108)
    Two scrapbooks containing an announcement of an award to Joseph W. Stilwell; a speech by him; a letter to the editor by Benjamin W. Stilwell, The Statesman, September 2, 1889; certificates issued to Joseph W. Stilwell by the U.S. Embassy in Madrid, Spain, July 9, 1914, and by the U.S. Consulate in Shanghai, China, May 16, 1923, entitling him to help and protection; a special order, issued July 1, 1928, directing Joseph C. Castner, Otto L. McDaniel, and Joseph W. Stilwell to proceed from Tientsin to Peking, China; Chinese paintings and notes; currency notes; clippings and printed matter; letters, including to Mrs. Joseph W. Stilwell; magazine subscriptions; memorabilia; military passes; name tags; notes; orders; party invitations; prints; postcards; propaganda materials dropped from airplanes over enemy lines; sketches; telegrams; and miscellany relating to Joseph W. Stilwell's life and military career.
  - Photographs, 1899-2000
    See also Scrapbooks.
    - 1 print depicting Joseph W. Stilwell with road engineer, General Pick, and driver Poh Braud, Peking, n.d.; 1 print depicting Joseph W. Stilwell bending on a table and writing in Chinese, n.d; 16 prints and 2 proof sheets depicting Joseph W. Stilwell's personal effects, including badge, belt, cap, a wooden box used to carry drinks for Joseph W. Stilwell ("Chariot II"), clothing, diplomatic passport, duffle bag, flag, first aid packet label, watch, and wooden name plate, undated (Box-folder 109: 1)
    - 1 print depicting Joseph W. Stilwell's hat, n.d.; 1 print depicting his shoes, n.d.; and 4 prints depicting Joseph W. Stilwell and Li-Jen Sun in jungles in Burma, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 109: 2)
    - 15 prints depicting the ceremony on the occasion of the issuance of the Stilwell Stamp, Providence, Rhode Island, and Stilwell Hall, Fort Ord, California, August 24-25, 2000, including John Easterbrook, Nancy Easterbrook Sherburne, Susan Mai Easterbrook Cole, and Leon Panetta. (Box-folder 109: 3)
    - 2 prints depicting Brehon Somervell, Chiang Kai-shek, Ho Ying-chin, Joseph W. Stilwell, Louis Mountbatten, and Mme Chiang Kai-shek, n.d.; 1 print depicting Louis Mountbatten and Joseph W. Stilwell, n.d.; and 1 print depicting Yonkers High School Football Team, 1899 (Box-folder 110: 1)
  - Oversize Materials, 1904-1945 (Box 111)
    Printed matter.
  - Memorabilia, circa 1945 (Boxes 112-113)
    Military binocular.
  - See PHOTOGRAPHS, undated (Box 114)
  - Sound recordings (Reading room workstation)
    Originals in Box 15.
    - Personal record, 1944 June 16; 2.0 discs
      Soldiers send audio messages home.
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0011984
    - Uncle Joe and the Boys, undated; 2.0 discs
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0011985
    - Chinese folk songs, undated; 1.0 discs
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0011989
    - Chinese folk songs, undated; 2.0 discs
      Part 1: Cuts 1-3 Part 2: Cuts 4-5 Part 3: Cuts 6-8 Part 4: [???]
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0012754
    - Red Barber Program, 1946 October 14; 1.0 discs
      Time: 6:30-6:45 64323 Copy
      Barber reflects on the life of General Stilwell as seen through the lens of sports, such as his interest in basketball at West Point and sports as a necessity in war--as a conditioning program for his soldiers and as a morale booster.
      The disc indicates this is a four part program. It appears the Hoover Institution only accessed one disc containing parts 1 and 2.
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0012757
    - Radio Address by General Stilwell on Army Day, 1946 April 06; 1.0 discs
      General Stilwell reflects on the state of the Army a year after the end of World War II. He argues the armed forces should be well-funded during peace time so that when it is called upon to fight another war, it is properly prepared.
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0012762
    - The Boss, Earnie, Joe, Ellis, and Paul from Burma, undated; 1.0 discs
      A message home from soldiers in the jungle.
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0012763
    - The Job Ahead, 1945 May 08; 1.0 discs
      General Stilwell looks at the challenges for the United States' military in Japan after defeating Germany in World War II.
      Two copies. One of the discs containing this program has an unrelated program, "From Burma," on its flipside. Please see 51001_a_0012767 for this program.
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0012766
    - From Burma, undated; 1.0 discs
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0012767
    - Rebuttal, 1950 January 22; 1.0 discs
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0012772
      This program was written by and delivered by Joseph Stilwell's widow. It focuses on the role Joseph Stilwell had in the loss of China to communism. Mrs. Stilwell responds to statements about his conduct.
    - Joseph Stilwell address to the San Francisco Chamber of Commerce, 1946 March 28; 5.0 discs
      General Stilwell speaks about the state of the United Stats' Army following the end of World War II.
      Part 1: Introduction Part 2: Leadership in the Pentagon Part 3: On good examples of military commanders and leaders Part 4: On the administration of nuclear weapons. Part 5: On the Army's efforts to dignify the enlisted soldier and reward excellence. Part 6: wishes and problems of the enlisted man, including uniforms, food, and how the treatment of rank-and-file compares to the treatment of officers. Part 7: More on differences between officers' and soldiers' lives. Part 8: On the need for discipline and the effectiveness of Army training. Part 9: Closing remarks."
      This talk is believed to be that which was described in the San Francisco Chronicle on March 29, 1946. The front page headline was, "Gen. Stilwell Talks Back: 'Army Caste System Sounds Nasty, but Discipline Is Vital.'" The article reports that Stilwell "covered the caste system, Army brass hats, the atomic bomb, and charges of undemocratic procedures in the Army," which closely parallels the arc of this recorded speech.
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0012773
    - General Dorn talk remembering General Stilwell, 1956 March 20; 3.0 discs
      General Dorn speaks before a gathering of people, including General Stilwell's widow.
      Dorn starts by speaking about the most controversial aspects of Stilwell's work in the China-Burma-India (CBI) theater. Topics he covers in order:
      - How Stilwell wound up in CBI instead of North Africa, where he was originally supposed to go. - Using Burma to supply China - The many interests by various nations that Stilwell had to balance.
      Following, he takes questions from the audience. The questions/audience are well picked up on the recording. Topics covered here include:
      - Stilwell's relationship with Chiang Kai-Shek and commanding the Chinese forces - Madame Chiang Kai-Shek, of whom General Dorn does not have a favorable opinion. Dorn analyzes her strengths, weaknesses, and others opinions of her. - What the implications would have been if an American corps was sent to China to assist the Chinese forces. - China going communist and American culpability for that. - The ability of China to act as an integrated power (audio quality is poor in this section due to a scratch on the accessioned disc) - Civil war in China prior to World War II. - The personality, political skills, and military skills of Chiang Kai-Shek - The future of Shanghai.
      The meeting ends with brief remarks from Mrs. Stilwell and one of General Stilwell's poems.
      The Frank Dorn Papers, 1927-1976, are also available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0012784
    - Warriors of Peace: Uncle Joe, undated; 3.0 discs
      Episode 31 of Warriors of Peace, a joint dramatic production from the American Broadcasting Company and the United States Army Recruiting Service.
      This production portrays General Joseph W. Stilwell.
      Use copy reference number 51001_a_0012800
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1917-1945
  - Records released in 2017, 1917-1945 (Reading room workstation)